Large Language Models, or LLMs, are increasingly
deployed in economics as powerful predictive
tools. They offer a cost-effective way to generate
synthetic responses and forecast economic
outcomes, embedding vast amounts of information.
However, a clear method to assess the quality and
true value of these LLM predictions has been
missing. We need a unifying metric to quantify the
benefits of substituting LLMs for human data.
This paper introduces the 'equivalent sample size'
(ESS), a novel measure that quantifies the domain-
specific value of LLMs in an interpretable unit:
the amount of human data they can effectively
substitute for.
ESS is defined as the smallest training sample
size required for a conventional machine learning
model, trained on that domain-specific data, to
match the predictive performance of a fixed,
pretrained LLM.
Quantifying ESS reveals that LLMs can exhibit
substantial heterogeneity. For some prediction
tasks, they are excellent data surrogates, while
for others, even minimal domain-specific data
quickly outperforms them.
Beyond introducing this measure, the paper
develops a robust method for estimating the ESS
and for conducting statistical inference,
including constructing confidence intervals
through sequential hypothesis testing.
The method is applied to the Panel Study of Income
Dynamics (PSID), a long-running U.S. longitudinal
household survey, to evaluate LLM predictions for
a suite of economic variables.
Our framework studies general prediction problems:
an analyst observes a covariate vector 'X' and
aims to predict an outcome 'Y'. The accuracy is
measured by an expected loss function.
The LLM-based prediction rule involves describing
the problem in natural language to a pretrained
LLM, whose response becomes the prediction. We
treat this LLM rule as fixed, without domain-
specific fine-tuning.
An example prompt might describe an individual's
demographic and work history, then ask the LLM to
predict their homeownership status, clearly
specifying output formats for interpretation.
We compare the LLM's error to a 'domain-specific
learning' approach, where a machine learning
algorithm is trained on increasing amounts of
observed (X, Y) data to produce prediction rules.
Figure 1 illustrates the equivalent sample size,
N*, as the point where the error curve of the
domain-specific algorithm drops below the constant
error level of the LLM prediction rule.
To estimate the LLM's benchmark error, e_LLM, we
calculate its empirical performance on the full
dataset by querying the LLM for each observation
and averaging the resulting losses.
The algorithm's error curve is estimated using a
block-out cross-validation procedure, where data
is split into disjoint training and test blocks to
evaluate out-of-sample performance.
Finally, a sequential hypothesis-testing procedure
compares the algorithm and LLM performance across
an ordered sequence of training sizes, providing a
reliable one-sided confidence interval for N*.
We establish the asymptotic properties of the
estimated variance, ensuring its convergence and
demonstrating that the studentized statistic
follows a standard normal distribution under
specific conditions. This forms the foundational
theoretical basis for our subsequent hypothesis
tests.
To construct a valid hypothesis test comparing the
estimated risks of machine learning models and
Large Language Models, we introduce a loss
difference function. This approach accounts for
correlations between models when computed on the
same dataset, crucial for fixed-N asymptotic
analysis.
Our Proposition 4.1 establishes the validity of
the studentized test statistic, Tdiff,Nk,n. Under
stated assumptions and the null hypothesis
boundary, this statistic asymptotically converges
to a standard normal distribution, confirming the
one-sided test's asymptotic size.
As a practical alternative to exact difference
variance, a conservative approach sums individual
variances. This often overestimates the true
variance due to positive correlation between model
errors, leading to a smaller test statistic and a
more conservative test.
We apply our framework to the Panel Study of
Income Dynamics (PSID), a longitudinal household
survey. We evaluate LLM prediction for four
outcomes: hourly wage, homeownership, smoking, and
drinking, utilizing detailed respondent
characteristics as covariates.
For continuous outcomes like hourly wage, we
employ squared-error loss and report RMSE. For
discrete outcomes such as homeownership, drinking,
and smoking, we use 0-1 loss, which translates to
the misclassification rate.
LLM predictions are generated by transforming
covariate vectors into natural language persona
descriptions. Critically, we do not fine-tune the
LLM on PSID data, and implement safeguards against
data leakage by using static models and post-
cutoff PSID releases.
For domain-specific learning, we benchmark LLM
performance against two popular supervised Machine
Learning algorithms: Lasso regression, a
regularized linear method, and Random Forests, a
flexible ensemble method for capturing complex
relationships.
We compute error curves for each ML model, showing
test error as a function of training sample size.
Hyperparameters are tuned via k-fold cross-
validation for every sample size, with results
presented through estimated error curves and
confidence intervals.
Our findings from Table 1 reveal substantial
heterogeneity in LLM predictive performance across
tasks. The equivalent sample size (ESS) of LLMs
varies widely, underscoring the task-specific
nature of their utility in empirical social
science.
The LLM demonstrates strong performance for
homeownership prediction, achieving an equivalent
sample size of at least 590 observations. Its
performance for predicting drinking behavior is
meaningful, with an ESS of at least 41
observations.
LLM performance deteriorates for hourly wages,
with an equivalent sample size of only 17-20
observations. For smoking behavior, the LLM
provides essentially no predictive value,
illustrating the extremes of its task-specific
capabilities.
Figure 3 illustrates the Root Mean Squared Error
(RMSE) for hourly wage prediction across varying
training sample sizes. The graph details how model
performance changes with increased data,
benchmarked against the LLM's error.
Figure 4 presents the misclassification rate for
homeownership prediction as a function of training
sample size. This visual shows the error curve for
domain-specific models, highlighting where LLM
performance aligns with traditional ML.
Figures 5 and 6 display the misclassification
rates for drinking and smoking behaviors
respectively. These graphs provide detailed error
curves across different training sizes, further
emphasizing the variability of LLM's predictive
utility in diverse contexts.